[Music]
foreign
the potent anti-hypertensive effect of
dietary flaxseed in hypertensive
patients this was a double randomized
placebo-controlled trial where they
disguised ground flaxseed and baked
goods versus like flax free Placebo
muffins and got an extraordinary drop in
high blood pressures as you can imagine
the flaxseed industry was overjoyed
praising the impressive findings as was
I after all high blood pressure is the
single largest risk factor for death on
the planet Earth
yes we give people medications lots and
lots of medications but most people
don't take them as in nine out of 10
people take less than 80 percent of the
prescribed blood pressure pills just
eight percent
it's not difficult to understand why
patients are asked to follow An
Inconvenient potentially costly regimen
which will likely have detrimental
effect on their health related quality
of life to treat it mostly asymptomatic
condition so they may feel worse instead
of better due to the side effects the
answer then is to give them more drugs
too counteract the effects of the first
drugs like giving men Viagra to counter
the erectile dysfunction caused by their
blood pressure pills how about using a
dietary strategy instead especially if
it can just be as effective and indeed
the drop in blood pressures they got in
the flaxseed study was greater than the
average decreased observed with the
standard dose of antihypertensive drugs
and flax seeds are cheaper too compared
to even single medications than most
patients are on multiple drugs and has
good side effects beyond their
anti-hypertensive actions but not all
good taking tablespoons of flaxseed a
day is a lot of fiber for people who've
been you know living off of
cheeseburgers and milkshakes their whole
lives it can take a little while for
your gut bacteria to adjust to the new
Bounty so people who start out with low
fiber diets may want to take it slow at
first
not all Studies have shown significant
blood pressure lowering effects there
have been over a dozen trials by now
involving more than a thousand subjects
and though yes you know put them all
together and overall there were
significant reductions in both systoc
and diastolic blood pressures the upper
and lower numbers following
supplementation with various flaxseed
products none were as dramatic as that
six-month trial the longer trials tended
to show better results and some of the
trials just used flaxseed oil or some
kind of flax seed extract and the
thought is that the whole is greater
than the sum of its parts
the components of interest within
flaxseed the Omega-3s the the
cancer-fighting lignans all the soluble
fiber and plant proteins all contribute
toward the blood pressure reduction okay
but how why right what's the mechanism
some common blood pressure medications
like Norvasc or Procardia work by
reducing the ability of the heart to
contract or slowing the heart down and
so it's possible that's how flax seeds
work too but no dietary flaxseed reduces
blood pressure without cardiac
involvement but rather through changes
in plasma oxylipins
what are oxy lipids oxy lipins a group
of fatty acid metabolites involved in
inflammation and as a result have been
implicated in many pro-inflammatory
conditions including cardiovascular
disease and aging the best characterized
oxy lipids in relation to cardiovascular
disease are derived from the long-chain
omega-6 fatty acids known as arachidonic
Acid found pre-formed in animal products
particularly chicken and eggs and can be
made inside the body from junky omega-6
Rich oil such as cottonseed oil but
elevated levels of pro-inflammatory oxy
lipids in older subjects are normalized
by flax seed consumption see that's how
we think flaxseed consumption reduces
blood pressure in patients with
hypertension by inhibiting the enzyme
that makes these pro-inflammatory
oxylipins also
spare you from the acronym overload but
basically eating flax seeds inhibits the
activity the enzyme that makes these
pro-inflammatory oxylipins called
leukotoxin dinos which in turn May lower
blood pressure identifying the molecular
mechanisms adds confidence to the
antihypertensive actions of dietary
flaxseed but that's not all oxy lipids
do oxy lipens may play a role in the
aging process but we may be able to
beneficially disrupt these biological
changes associated with inflammation and
aging with nutritional intervention like
flaxseed older adults around age 50 have
higher levels of these arachidonic acid
derived oxy-lipens compared to younger
adults around age 20. and these elevated
concentrations are pro-inflammatory
oxalip into the older age group may help
explain the higher levels of
inflammation in older versus younger
individuals I mean as we get older right
we're more likely to be stricken with
inflammatory conditions like arthritis
so this elevation of pro-inflammatory
oxy lipids May predispose individuals to
chronic disease conditions
but what if you took these older adults
and gave them muffins ground flaxseed
containing muffins four weeks later
their levels dropped to here right
down to like 20 year old levels
demonstrating that a potential
therapeutic strategy to correct the
deleterious pro-inflammatory oxylipin
profile is via dietary supplementation
with flax
[Music]
thank you